A Register of the David Lubin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
David Lubin papers
1899-1944
44005
Lubin, David, 1849-1919.; Saqui, Laura Lubin.
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 framed portrait (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives. Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, pamphlets, clippings, and photographs, relating to world agricultural problems, and activities of the International Institute of Agriculture. Includes papers of Laura Lubin Saqui, daughter of D. Lubin.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1944.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
David Lubin personal archive, David Lubin Memorial Library, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), Rome, Italy
Magnes collection on David Lubin, Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley
Simon Julius Lubin papers, Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley
Norris E. Dodd papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
10 June 1849 Born in Klodawa, Poland
1853 Family moved to England
1855 Family emigrated to America
1861 Dropped out of school
To 1873 Worked as a jeweler in San Francisco, a lumberyard worker in Los Angeles, a prospector for gold in Arizona, and a commercial traveler in New York and New Orleans
1874 Opened David Lubin's One Price Store in Sacramento
1884 Bought an orchard near Sacramento and land in Colusa County, helped found the California Fruit Growers' Union
1891 Became the director of the International Society for the Colonization of Russian Jews
1896 Moved to Europe to establish an international agricultural congress
1900 Author of Let There Be Light
1906 Appointed as a permanent U.S. delegate to the International Institute of Agriculture (IIA) in Rome
1913 Received a Silver Cup Award from the IIA
1917 Author, publisher, and distributor of An International Confederation of Democracies under a Constitution
1 January 1919 Died in Rome
Historical Note
David Lubin, a merchant and farmer in Sacramento, created the idea of the International Institute of Agriculture (IIA). The institute's goals were to help farmers share knowledge, establish a cooperative system of rural credit, and control the marketing of farmers' products. In 1906, Lubin was appointed the permanent U.S. delegate to the IIA. In 1913 at the meeting of the IIA congress in Rome, Lubin received a Silver Cup Award for his efforts in establishing the organization. The IIA ceased its operations in 1945, when most of its assets were transferred to the United Nations' Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO). The mandate of international cooperation in the field of agriculture is continued by the FAO, which named its library in honor of David Lubin. The David Lubin Elementary School is located a few blocks from the site of David Lubin's former home in Sacramento, California.
Scope and Content of Collection
Most of the papers relate to IIA operations and cover the period from 1905, when was IIA established, through 1944. The collection was donated to the Hoover Institution by Lubin's daughter Laura Lubin Saqui and includes her detailed "Table of Contents" (box 1), which is a useful finding aid to the Lubin papers.
The Laura Lubin Saqui files include business correspondence and writings, as well as her delegate certificate and a photograph. Laura Lubin Saqui was a U.S. delegate to the 15th General Assembly of IIA in 1940. The files also include letters written by Colonel Harris Weinstock, half brother of David Lubin, while he toured Europe as a member of the American Commission on Rural Cooperative Credit in 1913. The Scrapbooks of David Lubin and Laura Lubin Saqui contain documents related to Lubin's career and IIA operation, including official and private correspondence, records and reports, photographs, writings, and clippings.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
International Institute of Agriculture.; Agriculture.; International agricultural cooperation.
Collection Contents
- David Lubin files, 1899-1919. (Box 1)
  Includes some biographical material, correspondence,writings, and a portrait, arranged by physical form and chronologically therein. See also Scrapbooks
  - Biographical file, 1899-1919. (Folder 1: 1-2)
    Includes articles, clippings, and photographs
  - Correspondence, 1905-1919 (Folder 1: 3-5)
  - Writings, 1917-1918 (Folder 1: 6-7)
  - Framed portrait with caption: "From a painting of David Lubin by G. Szoldatics ordered by resolution of the General Assembly of the International Institution of Agriculture, Rome, 1910" (Box Art rack)
- Laura Lubin Saqui files, 1913-1944. (Box 1-2)
  Consists of a table of contents, correspondence, writings, and delegate certificate. Includes letters by Colonel Harris Weinstock. Arranged by physical form. See also Scrapbooks.
  - The David Lubin Collection. Table of Contents, typescript by Laura Lubin Sequi, 1944 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1941 (Folder 1: 11-12)
  - L. L. Saqui's certificate appointing her delegate to the 15th General Assembly of the International Institute of Agriculture (IIA) in May 1940., For accompanying letter from the U.S. State Department and a list of the U.S. delegation see box 1, folder 12 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Writings, 1932 (Folder 2: 1)
    Includes "The Status of World Agriculture," by Laura Lubin Saqui, 1932
  - Letters from Colonel Harris Weinstock, 1913 (Folder 2: 2)
- Files about the International Institute of Agriculture (IIA), 1918-1941. (Box 2)
  Contains U.S. documents concerning the IIA, general statements, and reports. Arranged by physical form. See also Scrapbooks
  - U.S. documents concerning IIA, 1918-1933 (Folder 2: 3-4)
  - Business cards of IIA officials, circa 1930 (Folder 2: 5)
  - A General Assembly general statements and reports, 1930-1940 (Folder 2: 6-9)
  - Materials on controversy over the IIA, 1931 (Folder 2: 10)
    Includes "The United States Government and the International Institute of Agriculture. The Facts in the Situation," by Simon J. Lubin, Chairman, Organizing Committee, Pan American Institute of Reciprocal Trade, March 18, 1931
  - The American Committee on the IIA memoranda and reports, 1933-1941 (Folder 2: 11)
- Scrapbooks (6), 1913-1936 (Box 3-5)
  Includes portfolios and envelopes of clippings, letters, photographs, leaflets, etc. Arranged by subject and chronologically therein.
  - David Lubin and International Institute of Agriculture (IIA), 1913-1933. (Box 3-4)
    Includes David Lubin, by A. Agresti, Rome, 1919
  - 12th and 13th Meetings of the General Assembly of the IIA, 1943-1936 (Box 5)